Aaron Apple

(847) 970-0924 • apple@cogsci.jhu.edu • linkedin.com/in/aaronapple

Profile

Recent graduate of the Department of Cognitive Science at Johns Hopkins University with a background in language processing and visual perception research and expertise in quantitative analysis and data visualization. Experienced in leading and managing research, with excellent interpersonal skills, intellectual curiosity, and a rigorous approach to solving complex problems.

Education

Johns Hopkins University

Baltimore, MD

Masters of Arts in Cognitive Science

Aug. 2015 - Aug. 2016

Linguistics Society of America

Chicago, IL

Graduate of the 2015 LSA Summer Institute at the University of Chicago

Jul. 2015 - Aug. 2015

New York University

New York, NY

Bachelors of Arts in Language and Mind, Minor in Creative Writing

Aug. 2008 - Dec. 2012

Professional Experience

Manager of the Language Processing and Development Lab

Baltimore, MD

Department of Cognitive Science, The Johns Hopkins University

Jan. 2013 - Jul. 2015

- Team leader on 2 eye tracking studies, developed hypotheses and designs, and conducted research and analysis.
- o Developed and maintained pipelines to manage, analyze, and visualize data for 12 experiments using R.
- Supervised 5 research assistants, providing training and establishing benchmarks and timetables.
- o Designed visual stimuli for 4 experiments using Adobe Illustrator, Photoshop & Anime Studio Pro.
- Wrote 5 articles submitted to peer-reviewed journals and presented at 2 conferences.
- Managed 3 IRB protocols, preparing submission materials and continuing reviews.
- Edited and revised 2 NSF grant proposals on child and adult language processing.
- Wrote, designed, and edited outreach newsletter describing lab activities using Adobe InDesign.

Research Assistant in the Davachi Memory Lab

New York, NY

Department of Psychology, New York University

May 2012 - Dec. 2012

- Assisted in programming MEG experiment on the time course of memory reactivation.
- Managed participant recruitment and data collection for 2 fMRI experiments.

Research Assistant in the Consciousness and Computation Lab

New York, NY

Department of Psychology, Columbia University

May 2012 - Dec. 2012

- Designed and coded psychophysics experiment on dynamic control of memory and attention.
- Managed participant recruitment and data collection for 3 behavioral experiments.

Research Assistant in the Neurolinguistics Lab

New York, NY

Department of Linguistics, New York University

Sept. 2011 - April 2012

- o Conducted literature review, developed hypothesis, and designed MEG experiment on semantic composition.
- Created battery of acoustic stimuli using Ableton Live and Audacity.

Editorial Intern at DVL Seigenthaler Public Relations Agency

Chicago, IL

• Wrote 12 press releases for 3 business clients.

- Aug. 2010 Dec. 2010
- Edited and fact-checked press releases and outreach magazines for 2 philanthropic clients.

Intern at 826CHI Chicago, IL

• Administered the after-school tutoring program of 30 children and tutors.

Aug. 2010 - Dec. 2010

• Taught writing in 2 English classes in a Chicago public high school.

Research Assistant for TerraLing (formerly SSWL)

New York, NY

Department of Linguistics, New York University

Jan. 2009 - June 2009

o Developed JavaScript tool to visualize phylogenetic and featural relationships between languages.

Publications, Presentations and Awards

Atkinson, E., **Apple, A.**, Omaki, A. (2016). Similarity of Wh-Phrases and Acceptability Variation in Wh-Islands. *Frontiers in Psychology*, 6.

Omaki, A, Lau, E. F., Davidson White, I., Dakan, M., **Apple, A.**, & Phillips, C. (2015). Hyper-active gap filling. *Frontiers in Psychology*, 6.

Apple, A. & Omaki, A. (2015). Incrementality and garden-path recovery in children's resolution of direct object vs. sentential complement ambiguity. Paper presented at the *Boston University Conference on Language Development 2015, November 13*.

Apple, A. & Omaki, A. (2015). Development of sentential complement ambiguity processing. Poster presented at the *CUNY 2015 Conference on Sentence Processing, March 21*.

Omaki, A. & **Apple, A.** (2014). Adaptation of active gap filling in coordinated sentences. Paper presented at *AMLaP* 2014, September 4.

Apple, A., Bemis, D., Marcus, G., Pylkkänen, L. (2012). Domain General Compositional Processing: An MEG Study. *Dean's Undergraduate Research Fund*, NYU. Poster presented at the Dean's Undergraduate Research conference and grant recipient of the highest award, \$1000.

Apple, A., Omaki, A. (In preparation). The role of incremental parsing on Japanese infants' word learning.

Apple, A., Omaki, A. (In preparation). Japanese infants' abstract knowledge of word order.

Apple, A., Omaki, A. (In preparation). Filler-gap processing in coordinate structures.

Apple, A., Omaki, A. (In preparation). Incrementality and garden-path recovery in child resolution of complement ambiguity.

Skills

Research: Eye tracking; Experimental design; Quantitative analysis; Data visualization; Scientific writing;

Public speaking; Data management; Research coordination; Grant editing; Corpus linguistics

Programming: R (advanced); Python (competent); MATLAB (competent); HTML (competent)

Software: Microsoft Office Suite; Adobe Creative Cloud; FileMaker Pro; Audacity; Ableton Live; SR Research Experiment Builder & Data Viewer

Statistical Methods: ANOVA; Mixed-effects regression; Bayesian inference; Neural networks

Languages: English (native); French (proficient)

Volunteering

Harwood Community Association

Baltimore, MD

Volunteer and organizer

Jul. 2015 - Aug. 2016

- Harwood's 2016 National Night Out Against Crime: Solicited food donations from local businesses, ran the BBQ grill, and assisted in managing other volunteers.
- The 2015 Ilchester Back to School Block Party: Solicited school supplies donations from local businesses and assisted in managing other volunteers.